<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>thwllms</title>
    <description>thwllms&#39; personal blog.</description>
    <link>http://www.thwllms.com/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.thwllms.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Countour Confusion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is something I run into a lot in the engineering/GIS world - a misunderstanding of contour data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, if you ask for a topographic dataset, you&amp;rsquo;re handed contours. They&amp;rsquo;re easy to understand and they look nice on a map. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://raw.githubusercontent.com/thwllms/blog/gh-pages/images/contours.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;So pretty.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem: many engineers forget that contours are one or more steps removed from the original topographic data. Somebody surveyed a bunch of points and fed the points into a GIS/CAD program to draw those those pretty lines. Contours are generated by interpolating between actual data points. They&amp;rsquo;re merely a visualization tool - they&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same or better than the original data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really problematic when it comes to LiDAR. If you paid for high-resolution LiDAR, there&amp;rsquo;s no sense in sharing the data as a set of 2-ft contours. That&amp;rsquo;s like taking a picture with a nice digital camera and distruting wallet-size photocopies instead of the original file, or watching a Blu-ray movie on an old CRT television. Sure, those 2-ft contours are handy, but they&amp;rsquo;re less accurate - especially in flat areas, steep areas, along roads, and in stream valleys. Basically, places where accuracy is really important. Between elevation 124 and elevation 126 you could be missing a lot of variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save the contours for your maps. Build a DEM from the raw data for actual analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 09:16:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.thwllms.com/blog/gis/2015/05/18/contours/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thwllms.com/blog/gis/2015/05/18/contours/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>git init</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to start a blog of sorts. I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see how this goes, eh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s some stuff I might write about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GIS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HEC-RAS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TMDLs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So&amp;hellip; maybe check back later. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2015 21:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.thwllms.com/blog/init/2015/05/16/first-post/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.thwllms.com/blog/init/2015/05/16/first-post/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
